Christos Mitropoulos

Email: chris.mitropoulos@gmail.com Mobile: +1-732-895-3357

Summary

Experienced Data Scientist with strong Data/Machine Learning Engineering skills that has mainly worked in the invalid traffic and fraud detection space and has a Cyber Security research background. Interested in full stack roles and solving problems end-to-end, from research to deployment and performance monitoring.

EXPERIENCE

Oracle Advertising - MOAT

New York, NY

Senior Data Scientist - Data Engineer

Jun. 2019 - present

My day to day responsibilities range from building end-to-end Machine Learning systems for identifying ad fraud using unsupervised and supervised techniques, to performing exploratory data analysis on ad measurement data for developing new invalid traffic detection methodologies.

- Developed Machine Learning based IP reputation metrics to flag suspicious IPs, while minimizing False positives.
- Built internal IP-Intelligence system that is responsible ingesting Terabytes of data daily and generating features. The system has monitoring and autoscaling capabilities and was built with cloud native tools.
- Automated and modernized a legacy data pipeline for producing quarterly Benchmarks across different cuts of our data. Decreased the engineering effort from 2.5 weeks to approximately 2 days, while making it easier to implement new features and product requests.
- o Tools: Python, scikit-learn, pandas, spark, pymc, SQL, linux, Airflow, Docker, Kubernetes, Argo Workflows, Grafana, Prometheus
- o Areas: Time-series analysis, anomaly detection, unsupervised / supervised learning, clustering, bayesian statistics, NLP

Perspecta Labs (former Vencore Labs, Applied Communication Sciences)

Baskin Ridge, NJ Jun. 2018 - Aug. 2018

Cyber Security Research Intern

• Developing botnets of the Fast Flux family, on top of the CyberVAN tesbed.

- Evaluating the performance of the botnets using intrusion detection systems and machine learning based techniques.
- o Tools: C++, Winsock, GoLang, Python, Linux and Windows operating systems.

Rutgers, The State University of New Jersey

New Brunswick, NJ

Research Assistant - HCI & Security Engineering Lab - Advisor: Prof. Janne Lindqvist

Sep. 2016 - May 2019

- o Forgetting of Passwords: Ecological Theory and Data published in USENIX Security '18 (top tier Cyber Security conference)
 - * Responsible for the neural network estimation of a password's strength section of the paper.
- Machine Learning and Social Protocols for Enhancing Spectrum Access
 - * Designed experiments for measuring user behavior under lossy networks and network connectivity sharing choices.
 - * Developed a novel video quality metric for longer videos, taking into account video freeze and frame distortions.
 - * Built a web-based tool to facilitate data collection.
- Analyze System Administrators' Vulnerability-handling Behavior
 - * Data mining on IPv4 network scanners and disclosed vulnerabilities datasets.
 - * Applied exploratory data analysis methods and created models with predictive power.

Rutgers, The State University of New Jersey

New Brunswick, NJ

Lead Teaching Assistant - Computer Architecture Lab

Sep. 2016 - May 2019

- Teaching Assembly MIPS to approximately 80 students.
- Preparing and grading lab assignments.

Rutgers, The State University of New Jersey

New Brunswick, NJ Jun. 2014 - Sep. 2014

Research Internship

o Research Areas: Pattern Recognition, Machine Learning, Security and Privacy, Human Computer Interaction

Digi4sites.com Athens, Greece

Software Engineer

Jun. 2012- Sep. 2014

• Responsibilities: Developing custom websites using HTML, CSS, jQuery, MySQL; Server administration using Amazon Web Services (AWS) tools.

EDUCATION

Rutgers, The State University of New Jersey, HCI & Security Engineering Lab

Masters in Electrical and Computer Engineering; Advisor: Prof Janne Lindqvist; GPA: 3.9

New Brunswick, NJ

Sep. 2016 - May 2019

- o Courses: Massive Data Mining and Learning, Parallel and Distributed Computing, Software Engineering, Regression Analysis, Security Engineering, Operating Systems
- o Online courses: Neural Networks and Deep Learning

National Technical University of Athens (NTUA)

Athens, Greece

Masters of Engineering in Electrical and Computer Engineering; GPA 3.6

Sep. 2010 - Sep. 2015

- o Thesis: Created an android based Gesture Authentication System using Machine Learning Models, Hidden Markov Models; Grade 10/10
- o Courses: Artificial Intelligence, Databases and Information Systems Engineering, Algorithms and Data Structures, Programming Languages, Computer - Communication - Mobile Networks

Programming Skills

- Languages: Java, Python, C/C++, MATLAB, Javascript, SQL
- Frameworks/Libraries: Scikit Learn, Pandas, Hadoop, SQL, AirFlow, Kubernetes, Argo, pthreads, ISPC, Django,
- OS: Linux, Windows

Honors and Awards

- 2018: Winner of the Rutgers State University TA/GA Development Fund
- 2017: Winner of the Gerondelis Foundation Grant

Academic Service

• SOUPS 2017, 2018: External Reviewer

• WWW 2018: External Reviewer

• IMWUT 2017: External Reviewer

Papers

• Xianyi Gao, Yulong Yang, Can Liu, Christos Mitropoulos, Oulasvirta Antti, Janne Lindqvist. "Forgetting of Passwords: Ecological Theory and Data", USENIX Security '18